Guide to the Christian Melchior-Bonnet Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Christian Melchior-Bonnet papers
1893-1986
1920-1986
GEN MSS 1153
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.76
(5 boxes)
Melchior-Bonnet, Christian
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Pierre Berès on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
Christian Melchior-Bonnet (1902-1995)
Christian Melchior-Bonnet, French journalist, editor, and author. Melchior-Bonnet was an editor of Le Petit Journal, Historia, and Journal de la France, and for the publisher Flammarion.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
Scope and Contents
The Christian Melchior-Bonnet Papers contain literary correspondence and writings of authors associated with Melchior-Bonnet. Most correspondence consists of letters to Melchior-Bonnet concerning his editoral work for Le Petit Journal and Flammarion; some is accompanied by outgoing carbons, or related memoranda and notes by Melchior-Bonnet, photographs, clippings, or other printed material. Correspondents include Paul Morand, represented by more than 200 letters, 1923-1976; other major correspondents are Pierre Champion, Roland Dorgelès, Marie Jeanne Durry, Jean-Jacques Gautier, Jean Giono, Victor Giraud, Emile Henriot, François Porché, and Jules Romains. Autograph manuscript writings include Morand's draft revision of Le voyage (Paris: Hachette, 1964); unidentified manuscripts by Henry Montherlant about his play Pasiphaë and essay collection Mors et vita; and other writings by Morand, Montherlant, Henry Bidou, Francis de Croisset, Victor Duruy, and others.
Petit journal (Paris, France); Editors -- France -- Archives; French literature -- 20th Century; Photographs -- France -- 20th Century; Editors -- France -- 20th Century; Bidou, Henry, 1873-1943; Champion, Pierre, 1880-1942; Croisset, Francis de, 1877-1937; Dorgelès, Roland, 1886-1973; Durry, Marie Jeanne, 1901-1980; Duruy, Victor, 1811-1894; Gautier, Jean-Jacques, 1908-1986; Giono, Jean, 1895-1970; Giraud, Victor, 1868-1953; Henriot, Emile, 1889-1961; Melchior-Bonnet, Christian; Montherlant, Henry de, 1896-1972; Morand, Paul, 1888-1976; Porché, François, 1877-1944; Romains, Jules, 1885-1972; Flammarion (Firm)
- Box and Folder List, 1893-1986
  Scope and Contents
  Writings are autograph manuscript, unless otherwise noted.
  - Achard, Juliette, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Achard, Marcel, 1955-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Achard, Marcel. Printed material, 1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Adam, Juliette, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alazard, Jean, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ambrière, Francis, 1946-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anet, Claude, 1923, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anet, Leila Claude, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Arbelet, Paul, 1925 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ariès, Philippe, 1954-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bauër, Gérard, 1947-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Besnard, Albert, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bidou, Gabriel, 1943, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bidou, Henry (includes writings), 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Billy, André, 1930-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Binet-Valmer, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bizet, Andrée, 1947 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bizet, René, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Boulenger, Jacques, 1922-1925 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Boulenger, Marcel, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brayer, Yves, 1969-1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Brieux, Eugène, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Brunetière, Ferdinand, 1893 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Champion, Pierre (includes writings), 1932-1940; 2 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Chapelain-Midy, Roger, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chevaly, Maurice, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Croisset, Francis de, 1930-1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Croisset, Francis de. Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Curel, François de, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Deharme, Lise, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Donnay, Maurice, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dorgelès, Roland (includes writings), 1922-1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Doumic, René, 1921-1927 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Dumur, Louis, 1923 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Durry, Marie Jeanne (includes photographs), 1927-1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Duruy, Victor. Histoire des Romains (fragment), undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Franc-Nohain, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Gautier, Jean-Jacques, 1948-1986 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Giono, Jean, 1935-1956; 2 (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
  - Giraud, Victor, 1919-1948 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Gyp, 1924 September (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Henriot, Emile, 1924-1958; 2 (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
  - Houssaye Guiroye, 1932-1939 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Larrouy, Maurice, 1930-1935 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Lavedan, Henri, 1923 February 23 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Lecomte, Georges, 1935-1956 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Le Goffic, Charles, 1923-1933 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Lemaître, Jules, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Lenormand, H.-R. (Henri-René), 1927 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Martin du Gard, Maurice, 1925-1962 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Maurois, André, 1939 December 4 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Mauron, Marie, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Mégret, Christian, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Mille, Pierre, 1922-1923 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Mondor, Henri, 1952-1960 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Montherlant, H. de (Henry). Writings
    Some writings are on versos of unidentified correspondence
    - "La guerre..douce à ceux qui ne savent pas", undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "Pourquoi j'ai ecrit 'Mors et vita'", undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Unidentified. "Avant-propos", 1938 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Unidentified. About performance of his play Pasiphaë (typescript and autograph manuscript), [1938] (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Unidentified. About Pour une vierge noire, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Morand, Hélène, 1949-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Morand, Paul, 1923-1976; 3 (Box 2, Folder 65-67)
  - Morand, Paul, 11 (Box 3, Folder 68-78)
  - Morand, Paul. Documents and correspondence about Morand, 1942-1982, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 79-80)
    Includes documents about Morand's literary and administrative activities between 1940 and 1944, typescript and typescript mimeograph, compiled at the time of his unsuccessful attempt to join the Académie française in 1958
  - Morand, Paul. Writings
    - Les Grands tournants de l'histoire. Preface, [1969] (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - "La jeune fille aux pivoines (a Chinese ghost story)...d'après la 'Folk-lore chinois' de R. P. Léon Wieger" (screenplay), undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Le voyage. Draft of revision (Paris: Hachette, 1964), autograph manuscript, with revised printed pages from 1927 edition, 1963-1964 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 106)
  - Pailleron, Marie-Louise, 1938-1949 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Pérochon, Ernest, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Plisnier, Charles, 1941-1947 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Porché, François, 1926-1943 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Poupet, Georges, 1937-1957 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Prévost, Marcel, [1923 September 24] (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Romains, Jules, 1948-1969 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Romains, Jules. Printed material, 1946-1985 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Roussin, André, 1950-1976 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Schlumberger, Jean, 1942-1943 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Soupault, Philippe (includes photograph), 1923 March 3 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Steinlen, Théophile Alexandre, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Supervielle, Jules, 1948 August 22 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Thérive, André, 1949-1963 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Thiébaut, Marcel, 1935-1952 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - T'Serstevens, A. (Albert), 1929, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Vaudoyer, Jean-Louis, 1962, undated (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Vautel, Clément, 1923, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Vildrac, Charles, 1945 August 8 (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Yamata, Kikou, no year January 15 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Zavie, Emile (includes photograph), 1926 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Zéraffa, Michel, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Zimmermann, Jacques, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 105)